<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-06T09:56:58-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Soft Surplus on art-washing, social technologies and friendship</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/05/in-conversation-with-soft-surplus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Soft Surplus on art-washing, social technologies and friendship" /><published>2019-01-05T19:39:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-05T19:39:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/05/in-conversation-with-soft-surplus</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/05/in-conversation-with-soft-surplus.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/soft-surplus1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Soft Surplus in the morning, days after the New York Tech Zine Fair. Image description: The Soft Surplus studio space which is a warehouse full of desks, boxes, storage units and green plants among other things.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Soft Surplus in the morning, days after the New York Tech Zine Fair. Image description: The Soft Surplus studio space which is a warehouse full of desks, boxes, storage units and green plants among other things. Photo courtesy Soft Surplus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I interviewed multi-disciplinary architectural, design and creative arts collective Soft Surplus, or SoSu for short. We exchanged messages digitally over a cloud sharing document editing service provider. Soft Surplus includes Angie Meitzler (AM), Austin Wade Smith (AWS), Dan Taeyoung (DT), Katie Giritlian (KG), Lai Yi Ohlsen (LO), Lucy Siyao Liu (LSYL). Melanie Hoff (MH), Rachel Haberstroh (RH) and Taylor Zanke (TZ). SoSu was a featured vendor at the first ever New York Tech Zine Fair on Dec. 1 at the School for Poetic Computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;In my experience, Soft Surplus is a bit hard to track down. I understand you’re all part of a newly formed collective, so I’m curious—what is Soft Surplus? Who is Soft Surplus? What do you all do?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWS: Soft Surplus is about 20 artists/designers/technologists who talk, eat, and make things together and individually. Every member has a different take on what it is, but I think we rally around the idea that we want our creative practice and life practice to be one and the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KG: It can feel like a soft framework to both anchor your practice and facilitate sharing that practice with others. A place where everyone is coming from various fields and modes of research, with generative overlaps revealing themselves through existing and orbiting in adjacency, softly so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DT: To me, Soft Surplus is a place to learn from each other by making things near each other; a place to be messy, curious, playful and empathetic. Sometimes I think of social collectives like gardens. Soft Surplus is a slightly wild, slightly messy, healthy, sunny garden with different plants growing in unexpected places and a nice spot to sit and watch the sunset together. The best way to understand a garden is to come and sit in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MH: My experience of Soft Surplus has been one of boundless learning and growing around and with the other members here. It’s a place for being generous and generative. We work on projects, water plants, share dumplings, make noise, whisper quietly, and move our bodies. Sometimes we make social technologies together like systems for collective decision making and other times we do our own thing. 
There’s a hole in my studio wall that separates mine and another member’s space where we haven’t finished putting up drywall. We often work quietly on either side of the gap. One day it will close and I will have enjoyed the breach in membrane as much as I will it’s patching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tell me about the “soft opening” party you hosted back in July this year. What was it like?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWS: Deadlines really help, and the soft opening was a great chance for us to formalize ourselves from all the ideas, conversations, and techniques we’d been sharing into a glowy, warm night of excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RH: For me, the soft opening highlighted the ways that Soft Surplus as a space can house exchange and play between communities that extend beyond our membership. It’s energizing to have a wide variety of collaborators and creative crushes all in one room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/soft-surplus2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image description: A photo of a dirty white jumpsuit with the word “soft” written in capital sans serif letters.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A photo of a dirty white jumpsuit with the word “soft” written in capital sans serif letters. Photo via &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/softsurplus&quot;&gt;Soft Surplus&lt;/a&gt; on Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What do the words: soft/surplus/hard/shortage mean to you?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWS: Surplus is a non-zero-sum kind of thinking. Collectively occupying a space creates opportunities in thought and relationship we couldn’t do alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DT: Soft means: to be generous and understanding, willing to grow; to have practices and rhythms. Surplus is a &lt;em&gt;spare&lt;/em&gt; moment of time to lend a hand to a friend, or the &lt;em&gt;extra&lt;/em&gt; coffee in the pot made just in case others wanted some. Hardness is the language of law, of exclusion and borders and unyielding rigidity; shortage is about the inability to accommodate others. Softness is curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RH: Soft, in the context of making beside one another, can manifest radical tenderness. Surplus means there’s more than enough to go around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MH: Soft skills, software, soft glow and soft voices being heard. Surplus dreams, care, and space to bring your dog. Hardness as something to push against or conform to. Shortage as constraints on how you move and practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/soft-surplus3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Soft Surplus members collectively building the mezzanine at their studio space.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Soft Surplus members collectively building the mezzanine at their studio space. Photo courtesy Soft Surplus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your studio space is located in East Williamsburg, a contentious Brooklyn neighborhood in the context of real estate development, New York transplants, artwashing, gentrification and the larger conversation of colonialism. How have you navigated these issues inside and outside of your work?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LO: I’ve thought of Sarah Schulman’s &lt;em&gt;Gentrification of the Mind&lt;/em&gt; many times since joining SoSu. She speaks to the difference between those who move into areas to build something that isn’t welcome elsewhere and those who move into areas to replicate something that already exists elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DT: Yes. East Williamsburg is fraught with the exact reasons you mention. In my personal work, I’ve been part of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://nycreic.com/&quot;&gt;NYC Real Estate Investment Cooperative&lt;/a&gt;, which is an anti-displacement effort to cooperatively fund commercial real estate in order to stabilize and support existing communities. To me, it’s a form of ‘activist real estate’—creating community land trusts against real estate speculation. I’ve also co-created &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.landscapesofprofit.com/&quot;&gt;Landscapes of Profit&lt;/a&gt;, a project visualizing a one percent ‘flip tax’ on flipped properties—properties bought and sold within two years—that would go towards affordable space in NYC. 
For Soft Surplus, personally speaking, it’s important to me that we can be critical of ‘creative class’ consumption culture that aids speculation and artwashing, especially considering our location in East Williamsburg. Instead, we can create a place that can support creating, producing, experimenting, and learning. To me, that means trying to create &lt;em&gt;‘&lt;/em&gt;community infrastructure’—creating a collectively run space without profit motives, that can support a collective through shared social and spatial resources. It also means being hesitant about being public-facing, such as in interviews like this one!
One form of critique against a speculative real estate market that financializes space is to engage with it in practice, rather than withdrawal. I think more artists, designers, organizers, educators, researchers should become real-estate savvy, and create more spaces to support communities. Ideally, the land should be owned as community land trusts and the building structured as a limited-equity cooperative, structurally designed to limit long-term speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What other issues or subjects are you exploring in your zines?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWS: The visual language of future nation states populated by non-human life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KG: SURPLUS is a monthly, internal zine for Soft Surplus members to exchange, respond and share. Not limited in medium, our collection includes CDs, pamphlets, posters and other printed and digital matter. Some issues function as a framework to facilitate exchange amongst all members, such as a CD we made in June and a forthcoming oral history project; whereas, others provide a chance for a couple of members to meet and collaborate who may not have had a chance to prior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DT: Social technologies for facilitation, organizing and discussing things in a group. How do we talk together? How do we make decisions together? Exercises are informal social technologies that can enact and change how we understand each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MH: I’m interested in how children conceptualize beings without bodies, about how they learn which names and voices go with which genders, and how they begin to understand technology, identity, obedience, and gender norms. “Draw What You Think Alexa Looks Like” is a collection of drawings by children in response to the titular question. 
For the New York Tech Zine Fair, I also worked on designing and editing a zine for the Cybernetics Library about social, reproductive and conversational cybernetics along with other members of the Cybernetics Library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TZ: I’m working on a book that has to do with the recall and invention of place, both actual and plausible. In the case of the book, the places are constructed of memories, plausible, real, emotional, spiritual, aspirational, that I think I might share with those who I have descended from. I used this zine as an opportunity to sketch out some ideas about where those places may be, in past or present, and to think about the emotional content of the images I tend to see on my screens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is your personal relationship with technology like?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LY: I have a giant, wary crush on technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWS: It’s complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DT: I love technology the same way I like language. I enjoy reading. I think the best kind of literature is the kind that explores ideas and asks questions of the world. I think the worst kind of language is when it becomes mobilized with power and money and used for harm or endless profit. I cherish the novels of technology and critique the predatory contracts of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AM: It’s a tool and a medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RH: I think about the way technology can privilege, narrativize, redact or obscure my identities (being white, queer, millennial, etc). It’s hard for me to separate technology as a tool from technology as an industry. Tackling the problematic narratives of the technology industry is what a lot of my work is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TZ: It’s something that I work on as a designer and have given really little thought to as an artist. I’m grappling with its placelessness and timelessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LSYL: Sometimes technology doesn’t necessarily look like technology. Been trying to educate myself and others what it means to our creative work now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/soft-surplus4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Soft Surplus members tabling at the New York Tech Zine Fair. Image description: Three people sit and stand behind a table filled with zines and other printed matters, happily smiling and looking at the camera.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Soft Surplus members tabling at the New York Tech Zine Fair. Image description: Three people sit and stand behind a table filled with zines and other printed matters, happily smiling and looking at the camera. Photo via &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/softsurplus&quot;&gt;Soft Surplus&lt;/a&gt; on Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you consider zine making itself a technology?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KG: Yes! I think of it as a technology in 2 distinct ways: First, the technology of a bound item disseminating information or narrative independently of an existing, dominant means and second, because of my background in printed matter, I think about the technologies around paper, the printing press, and book assembly and the ways those various technologies (and their histories) informed choreographies of reading. With my background, I have felt so grateful to participate in a diverse community such as Soft Surplus where I can learn how the ethos of zines relate to the ethos of P2P, distributed web of care, etc. I am very excited to see these connections furthered at the New York Tech Zine Fair!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RH: Technologies within technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What media are you all into right now? Have you found anything particularly inspiring?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoSu: Paper, movement, CNC drag knives, acrobatics, print, paint, wood, steel, object tracking, drawing, singing, sewing, resin, knitting, spreadsheets, communications, shared documents, local area networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What’s next for Soft Surplus?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
AWS: Cozy studio hangouts as the snow starts to fall. Our 1 year anniversary is soon too. That’s exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MH: We’re thinking about ways to support lightweight residencies here and have more potlucks. 
SoSu: More projects, dinners. More reading groups.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Neta Bomani</name></author><summary type="html">Soft Surplus in the morning, days after the New York Tech Zine Fair. Image description: The Soft Surplus studio space which is a warehouse full of desks, boxes, storage units and green plants among other things. Photo courtesy Soft Surplus.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Detroit Community Tech Project on autonomous communities, the confluence of organizing, technology and the liberation of data bodies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/05/in-conversation-with-dctp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Detroit Community Tech Project on autonomous communities, the confluence of organizing, technology and the liberation of data bodies" /><published>2019-01-05T17:27:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-05T17:27:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/05/in-conversation-with-dctp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/05/in-conversation-with-dctp.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/dctp1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Digital stewards of DCTP Heru House and Gabrielle Knox. Photo via Jean Louis Farges. Image description: Two people stand behind a table covered with electronic equipment necessary to set up wireless internet.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Digital stewards of DCTP Heru House and Gabrielle Knox. Photo via Jean Louis Farges. Image description: Two people stand behind a table covered with electronic equipment necessary to set up wireless internet. Photo courtesy DCTP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I interviewed community researcher Tawana Petty and program coordinator Janice Gates from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://detroitcommunitytech.org&quot;&gt;Detroit Community Tech Project&lt;/a&gt; (DCTP). DCTP works around building digital media education and community technology in Detroit. DCTP was a featured vendor at the first ever New York Tech Zine Fair on Dec. 1 at the School for Poetic Computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tell me a little bit about yourselves—who you are, what your role in DCTP is and what’s going on in your world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tawana: This is Tawana Petty. I am the data justice coordinator for the Detroit Community Tech Project as well as a data justice researcher. And I serve as a communications assistant. Currently, I maintain our social media profile as well as our research around data justice and some of the policies and things that are happening in the city around surveillance and technologies. I’m currently digging into our city infrastructure as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.greenlightdetroit.org/&quot;&gt;Project Green Light&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/decennial-census/2020-census.html&quot;&gt;Census 2020&lt;/a&gt; and convening our Detroit Digital Justice Coalition around organizing efforts on those three fronts. And I co-lead a three-city [Charlotte, North Carolina; Detroit, Michigan, and Los Angeles, California] participatory research project called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.odbproject.org/&quot;&gt;Our Data Bodies&lt;/a&gt; which we will be launching a digital defense playbook through that effort. Those are my current roles within DCTP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can you tell me a little bit more about Project Green Light?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T: Project Green Light is this collaboration with the Detroit Police Department. It’s kind of like a mandate for businesses that are open late to have cameras installed that can be monitored by, not only the police department, but community members who are volunteer citizens that monitor these businesses for crime, essentially. I’m not really sure yet whether community members have this part of it as well, but officers have an app on their cell phone where they can then monitor from wherever they are. It’s essentially a ramped up method of surveillance under the guise of safety. 
What we are researching is whether or not surveillance creates safety. Although my research with the Our Data Bodies project shows an analysis between the three cities around surveillance not creating safety, but we want to make sure that with regard to this particular project that we have fresh research and fresh analysis, that we talk to the foundations that are funding this smart city infrastructure and these technologies and make sure that we can come out with our analysis backed up in such a way that brings all the voices into the fold.
But because Detroit has suffered under a half century of propaganda assault and some community members have internalized that in maybe some function or particular way, as well as community members have internalized that who have not experienced crime, it’s easy to opt into things that create unsafe infrastructure. If you’re afraid and convinced to be afraid, then you’ll ask for the things that aren’t safe for you like surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I wanna talk more about that later, but first, I want to know a more about who you are, Janice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Janice: My role at DCTP is I’m the coordinator for the Equitable Internet Initiative (EII). I really support the anchor organizations we work with on about three levels. I work with the project managers to plan for network sustainability, resiliency and staff management. Each anchor organization also has a network manager and those network managers plan the work of the stewards. So, I meet with them, really more around administrative and management support. And then, I work with the digital stewards to support them in building out the actual networks. I help coordinate more intensive technical trainings they might need—any documents or resources they don’t have, and provide logistical support for meetings, events and any activities involving the stewards. This year, we’re working on a plan to make the networks completely autonomous by the end of 2019 to were they won’t be so reliable on us for support, it’ll move more into a collective or a network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you think it’s important to bridge the gap between the organizing and tech communities? Do you see these communities as separate in the first place? If so, why or why not?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T: It’s tremendously important to bridge the gap between the organizing and tech communities. It’s one of the reasons why I am, essentially, a social justice worker first and a technologist second. It’s very important, especially within research, to have that community, grassroots, organizing perspective because—I mean we’re all flawed, so you can’t give a guarantee, but—it’s the way that we bring community members into the fold when we’re making decisions and it’s the way that you know how to approach community about the things that they need versus parachuting in and creating things that aren’t going to serve the community. When you are an organizer, you tend to see yourself as part of the community and not someone that is apart from the community. So you’re making decisions not only for people that would be outside of your work, but yourself as well. When you look at it from that perspective, you use a co-liberatory framework instead of like, ‘hey, I’m an ally. I’m coming in. I’m going to help you do this thing,’ you’re looking at as ‘this is something that is going to best serve all of us.’ It’s a more holistic way of doing the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J: Which is part of the reason we included organizing in the digital stewards curriculum. So the students went through a 16 week training and they actually spent half of that time learning how to organize. We looked at organizing as a way to get residents in the communities to take more ownership of the network, which is why we spent a lot of time teaching the stewards how to do that. They’ve been using those organizing tools that they learned to work with the neighborhood advisory boards, set up community meetings and workshops, and a couple of the groups go door to door and get people to sign up for the network. It’s also how they educate them about what the network is, how far it extends, and the benefits of being part of the EII network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;You both emphasize passing on technical skills onto people within the community. What do you consider full autonomy?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T: [Sighs] I’ll let you take that one, Janice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Laughs]. It’s a big question.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J: I look at it as more than just being able to download at super fast speeds, but also like, thinking about what else can you create on this network that can benefit you, your family, or your community at large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T: One of the significant things about EII and the work that Janice is doing within EII is that these are community members that are essentially working with their neighbors, within their neighborhoods. The things they’re doing within the Equitable Internet Initiative becomes more autonomous because they’re not consumers, this is something that they’re co-creating. This is something that they’re defining for their neighborhoods specifically, based on the needs they’re neighbors are telling them. They’re not just looking at this as ‘oh, I’m going to have this thing that’s exterior to me that I can then consume, consume, consume from.’ They’re looking at a cooperative, productive manner of how to create a more self determinant community. It’s really bigger than just having internet access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/dctp2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Opening Data Zine by DCTP and the Detroit Digital Justice Coalition. Image description: Three zine printouts stacked on top of each other. The one on top reads “opening data” in big, bold, cyan capital letters in a sans serif font.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Opening Data Zine by DCTP and the Detroit Digital Justice Coalition. Image description: Three zine printouts stacked on top of each other. The one on top reads “opening data” in big, bold, cyan capital letters in a sans serif font. Photo via Allied Media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yeah, absolutely. So far, you’ve released 5 or so zines with the Detroit Digital Justice Coalition. How does zine making fit into DCTP’s larger goal to use and develop technology that connects people back to each other and the earth?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T: &lt;em&gt;Ashe&lt;/em&gt;. Great question. Anything we do and learn, we feel it’s important to pay forward. The zines provide an opportunity to share the information as well as train trainers within our community to produce the things we’re doing in such a way where people can take ownership of them, as Janice was saying earlier. Basically, we try to create the thing they need for self determination. The zines make it accessible, because, as you know, the reason why EII exists in Detroit is because more than 35 percent of the city doesn’t have access to broadband. We don’t want the information to sit and wait until community members have digital access, we want to make sure they have access to these tools at the very basic technical level, which we know, a zine is also technology. So not just digital infrastructure, but analog infrastructure as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J: It’s also shared with them in a way that’s easily accessible. In our zines, there’s not a lot of tech jargon that most people wouldn’t understand. I think there’s a zine coming out on how the internet works, which can be a very complicated thing to look at, but this zine breaks it down and lets people know how things work, like how is your information being used and where is it being used. It’s also about how it’s shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let’s say DCTP decided to start working on a zine project today. What would that process be like?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T: Well, we normally lock each other together in a room for days and brainstorm our passions. Like, what’s the thing we think is important to bring to this creative process. Then we spend time working on that thing, and then we come together and streamline what we’ve created. Depending on the length of the zine, how complex it is or whether or not it’s going to be in the curriculum, we think about who can take particular lessons and flesh those out, what are some research and resources we need to look into and then we come back together. It’s a very collaborative process of brainstorming, co-creating content and then someone will do copyediting and someone will do design, but we’re collaborative all throughout the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a black woman, I’m really curious about your personal relationships with technology and also what it’s like being surrounded by other black women within the collective, non profit, tech space that you’re in. How does that impact the work you do?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T: For me, it’s tremendous. It goes against the dominant narrative that black women are not technologists, that black women don’t have information around digital infrastructure, that we can’t teach technical skills, that we’re just not within this work. What is the significance of our data bodies? It’s tremendous to be so involved with black women and other women of color who are kicking ass in this work. Like I said, it defies all the narratives that have defined this work for &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; long and it’s empowering. It feels good to wake up everyday to know that I’m a part of this.
J: It’s a very freeing space to be in, working with all women of color, especially leading this project. Because we’re not playing by anyone’s rules. We’re not doing technology the way everyone says or suggests it should be done. We’re showing people there’s a different way to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/dctp3.png&quot; alt=&quot;DCTP Gigabit Workshop with Mozilla Foundation. Image courtesy the Detroit Community Tech Project.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;DCTP Gigabit Workshop with Mozilla Foundation. Image courtesy the Detroit Community Tech Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;It means a lot for me to see two black women doing the work that you do within tech. On that note, I want to talk about the statistic that 40 percent of people in Detroit don’t have internet access. It’s almost been a year since that statistic has been released. How have you seen your community change as a result of your efforts?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T: There’s definitely a bit of research on what our impact has been on that number. I can personally say, from the data justice perspective, the biggest impact I’ve seen is consciousness around who can access, who can create their own internet, who can be brought into this conversation, what capacity do we have to create cooperative infrastructure around technology. Whereas, if I were to try to pose this conversation five years ago, it would be more difficult and imagining black women in it would definitely not be a big part of the equation. I’ll also say, the work through the Digital Justice Coalition, for many years now, has been tremendous within collaborating on all these avenues and organizing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alliedmedia.org/ddjc/discotech&quot;&gt;Data DiscoTechs&lt;/a&gt; which is short for ‘discovering technology.’ A lot of the folks that are now digital stewards have had some communication coming through the Data DiscoTechs or being at different Allied Media conferences. There’s been a long history of having the conversation, but EII being a very solid, sound infrastructure and example. Now we get to put the consciousness with the visible infrastructure. I can imagine that even if the percentage is small at this point, the potential is large because the consciousness has shifted. That’s the biggest part, having community members having the faith and courage that they can make this kind of impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J: Where I’ve seen it have impacts is among the digital stewards. A lot of them came only as technologists or organizers, and in watching the growth of how they’ve taken ownership over building wireless internet infrastructure, it’s more than just a job to many of them. They’re building relationships with residents on the network in a way that larger ISPs [Internet Service Providers] don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What does a caring, digitally literate, consensual world look like to you?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T: Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J: Hm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;T: Honestly, we’re not there yet, but we’re as close as one can get. I talk about this all the time—I work part time and there are days I don’t have to be here, but I find myself coming into this space voluntarily. I’ve been in a corporate world and I’ve been in this world. I would, as one of my late mentors would say, ‘we’re making the road by walking it.’ But it’s definitely a road I’m happy to be on. I think asking more questions, questioning whether we’re being consentful, questioning whether safety and security are synonymous or not. A lot of questioning and not accepting the status quo and imagining what we want to create. We actually innovate and create what we imagine on a daily basis which is not the freedom that a lot of other places have. Personally, I don’t know what that world would look like, but if we think about what it would look like, we start to build a curriculum around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I think that’s a beautiful point that you bring up, because you’re involved in organizing and surrounded by a community where you’re able to imagine the world you want to see on a daily basis, maybe your world already looks like that. People who are outside of organizing might have a different purview because they’re not surrounded by people making the changes they want to see. But you’re seeing the world through the lens of other organizers and people who are very much engaged in enacting the world they want to see.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J: I don’t know if either of you have seen &lt;em&gt;Life of Pi&lt;/em&gt;, but there’s a point where Pi is on this island where he’s looking down into the water and the water’s green. He realizes the water is only green on that specific island, that that’s the only place it changes colors. I just feel like we’re kind of on that magical island. The water just needs to spread. We’ve laid the foundation, we’ve built the infrastructure, now we just need more digital stewards. I think this blend of technology and organizing will be responsible for spreading that type of magic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Neta Bomani</name></author><summary type="html">Digital stewards of DCTP Heru House and Gabrielle Knox. Photo via Jean Louis Farges. Image description: Two people stand behind a table covered with electronic equipment necessary to set up wireless internet. Photo courtesy DCTP.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wren McDonald on living in a cyberpunk world, zines as art objects and 90s nostalgia</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/11/27/in-conversation-with-wren-mcdonald.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wren McDonald on living in a cyberpunk world, zines as art objects and 90s nostalgia" /><published>2018-11-27T16:35:06-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-27T16:35:06-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/27/in-conversation-with-wren-mcdonald</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/11/27/in-conversation-with-wren-mcdonald.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/wrenmcdonald1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wren McDonald&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An illustration of Wren McDonald drawing by Wren McDonald. Image description: A cartoon of a boyishly looking person hunched over a drafter’s desk with a backpack on. The person is drawing a smiley face sticking its tongue out. There is also a mechanical cord attached to the back of the person’s head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I interviewed illustrator and cartoonist &lt;a href=&quot;https://wrenmcdonald.com/&quot;&gt;Wren McDonald&lt;/a&gt;. Not only has Wren’s work been featured in publications such as &lt;em&gt;the New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wired&lt;/em&gt; and Boom! Studios, but Wren is also preceded by a long line of artists engaged in the cyberpunk genre, from Paul Verhoeven to Katsuhiro Otomo. Wren will be a vendor at the first ever New York Tech Zine Fair on Dec. 1 from 12-7 p.m. at the School for Poetic Computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tell me a little bit about yourself—what’s going on in your world?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wren: My name is Wren McDonald. I’m a cartoonist and illustrator. I make comics, mostly science fiction comics leaning towards cyberpunk. I have a graphic novel called &lt;a href=&quot;https://nobrow.net/shop/sp4rx/&quot;&gt;SP4RX&lt;/a&gt; published by Nobrow which came out about a year and a half ago. I also self publish a lot of my own mini comics and zines that revolve around the same subject matter. I also do a lot of  editorial illustrations for magazines and newspapers such as &lt;em&gt;the New York Times&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;New Yorker&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;You mentioned a lot of your work has a cyberpunk, and I kind of get this tech-dystopian, hacker feel to it. Do you identify as a hacker or programmer?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: I don’t, actually, but it’s something that I’ve always been attracted to. I think that has a lot to do with growing up in the ‘90s and the things I was exposed to. Because for cyberpunk, the hayday in popular culture was definitely the ‘90s coming out from the real actual content in the ‘80s, and it becoming mainstream in the ‘90s. Being exposed to movies like &lt;em&gt;Terminator 2&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Total Recall&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;the Matrix&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Hackers&lt;/em&gt;. I think that had a big impact on me. Also around that time was the anime and manga boom of the ‘90s. A lot of that stuff was also really science fiction or cyberpunk heavy. One title that a huge affect on me was &lt;em&gt;Akira&lt;/em&gt; by Katsuhiro Otomo. Also &lt;em&gt;Ghost in the Shell&lt;/em&gt; by Mamoru Oshii. &lt;em&gt;Blame!&lt;/em&gt; by Tsutomu Nihei. &lt;em&gt;Evangeli&lt;/em&gt;—you know [laughs]. Just growing up in that. Not only that, but when I was a kid, not everyone had internet or computers in their homes. Now everyone has it in their pocket. Being there when the internet became a common tool that everyone used I think is really interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do you feel about being categorized within the cyberpunk, hacker aesthetic? Have you thought about breaking outside of that?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: I feel like categorizing my work as cyberpunk gives people an entry point into what I do—like if you like cyberpunk, you might be interested in this. I don’t feel constrained to only do cyberpunk genre work. I’ve always been really interested in science fiction in general and some of my other work breaks into that. But I’ve also done a lot of other stuff, especially all of my editorial work, a lot of the jobs I work on have nothing to do with technology in anyway. So, yeah, I don’t think it’s crucial to me that I’m identified as like a ‘cyberpunk artist’ or something, but I think it can help in terms of introducing people to my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How does your personal relationship with technology inform the comics you’re creating?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: I think that’s something that’s really interesting about cyberpunk as a genre in that, we kind of live in a cyberpunk or techno-dystopian world now. The aesthetics aren’t there yet, but day to day, government agencies and corporations are collecting your data, listening in, using it and putting a lot of energy and money into manipulating you. That’s the story we’ve been hearing for so long. And so I think the genre is still so relevant. I think it’s fun to use the tropes that are really campy now to talk about something that’s still so real and happening everyday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do you approach embedding politics or criticality into your work?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: I don’t try to overthink it too much. I just respond to what’s happening around me. When I was working on my graphic novel SP4RX, I would watch the news every morning before I sat down to start working on it and a lot of times whatever was in the news that morning worked its way into the pages I was working on that day. I don’t think that I ever sit down with a really clear agenda. Everything I’m exposed to on a day to day basis works its way in. I think it’s really important, obviously, to pay attention to what’s going on around you. That makes the work relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;You make a distinction between comics and illustration in your work. How do you approach a comic versus an illustration project? Do you also think of your zines separately as well?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: I definitely do. I feel like the comics and zines are much more personally driven work, so I feel like that’s much more “me” or maybe a purer sense of my point of view. Because a lot of times with illustration, I’m being commissioned to make an illustration for a magazine, newspaper or website that’s about someone else’s ideas. Sometimes I do like the personal illustration just for myself, but I feel like much more often I’m able to put personal energy into the comics and zines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What sort of things do you think about when you sit down and make a zine?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: When I’m working on a comic or zine, I’m always thinking about the finished product. Even when I start drawing the first page, I really like to think ‘what is this going to feel like in the reader’s hands?’ I put a lot of thought into sizing and color and how it’s going to feel when they flip from page to page. Something I use for all my zines is a risograph copy machine. That’s something I was introduced to maybe, five years ago. It’s a really cool copy machine that allows you to print one color at a time, so the final effect is similar to screenprinting. It’s really fast and effective if you’re planning on making zines or askance, throwaway flyers—stuff like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/wrenmcdonald3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wren McDonald&quot; /&gt;
 Wren at the School of Visual Arts RisoLAB. Image courtesy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Bp70WREh6_C/&quot;&gt;Wren McDonald&lt;/a&gt;. Image description: Wren posing down on one knee with a peace sign next to a risograph machine. A black ink cartridge is extended out toward the center foreground of the image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, right now, I’m the artist in residence at the School of Visual Arts RisoLAB, which has been great because their facilities are really nice. With the risograph, they’re always really finicky and I’ve owned my own and it’s always kind of a headache when you’re working on a zine like ‘is the machine gonna break down? I hope it doesn’t like, explode [laughs]. I hope I don’t run out of this supply or that supply.’ Those factors aren’t something I have to worry about at RisoLAB.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have you experienced any happy accidents from the risograph that you’ve tried to duplicate in your work?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: Definitely. One thing that I think is really cool about risographs is that it adds an element of surprise to the final product. The registration, meaning the alignment of the colors, is not always exact. The texture can be a little bit off, sometimes there will be a small hole or scratch in the screen and you’ll get this textural effect which I think is really interesting. With my work, I’m using a lot of tropes from the ‘80s and ‘90s. The texture of the risograph has plays into that as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How would you describe your relationship with the people who read your comics and zines?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: The way I interact with everyone who reads my work is primarily online. It’s funny because the whole world kind of exists there. When I do a show, it’s really interesting and really cool, to be honest, to see the people who I’ve interacted with online in real life. It just adds a physicality to it, like &lt;em&gt;this is real&lt;/em&gt;. I think it’s cool to exist in a physical space and be able to talk zines and comics and everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do you think technology factors into the context of zinemaking and the zine community today?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: Zines hold a different space than they used to when they were first a thing. With the punk movement and everything, it was out of a necessity to get ideas out there and there was no other way to do that. Magazines or book publishers wouldn’t publish their ideas so, people were like ‘okay, I’m just going to go to the Xerox store, make these really cheaply and get the idea out there.’ Now with the internet and social media and everything, it’s so much easier to get your ideas out there, especially with something like Twitter. I think zines are now becoming more of an art object. I see zines becoming more and more expensive. I feel like it’s no longer a necessity. I don’t know, there’s a little bit of overlap there where it’s still about getting your idea out there and it’s especially really significant to be able to hand your idea to someone physically. At least in the comics zine community that I’m a part of, people are going there to get something from an artist that they like and primarily people already know what they’re getting themselves into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the current political moment where the corruption of the American government is at the forefront of public consciousness, how can we be critical with our work when this administration is shameless?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: If we can do anything we can to point out the ridiculousness that’s going on, then hopefully we can contribute in some way to changing the public opinion that this is normal. Yeah, I don’t know if my cyberpunk zine is going to change the world—obviously not, but hopefully it can contribute a drop in the bucket to the few people that actually read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/wrenmcdonald2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wren McDonald&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Precinct X99 Episode 1 by Wren McDonald. Image description: Wren McDonald holding the cover of Precinct X99 which shows a femme character in the background firing a pistol to the right, a masculine character in the foreground lowering a recently fired pistol and a dog sticking its tongue out between the two of them. The comic is colored in blue and red with a faded textural effect most likely achieved by a risograph printer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What sort of things are grounding you right now? What are you inspired by?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: To be honest, I love the same thing I’ve always been interested in which is science fiction from the ‘80s and ‘90s. Comics wise, I’m really into a series called &lt;em&gt;Eden: It’s an Endless World!&lt;/em&gt; by Hiroki Endo. I just started re-watching &lt;em&gt;Neon Genesis Evangelion&lt;/em&gt;, which is a favorite of mine. I don’t only expose myself to the older stuff. I still like going and seeing what’s new out there, especially when it comes to indie comics. I just did Comic Arts Brooklyn earlier this month and it’s so cool to walk around and see what everyone is doing and printing there and seeing how people are really pushing zinemaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are you looking forward to in terms of the New York Tech Zine Fair?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: I’m actually really excited about this fair because I feel like all the shows that I usually do are illustration and comic space. It’ll be really cool to have my work, which is primarily about technology in a space that is focused on that and be able to have people interact with my work and interact with others’ work who are also interested in science and technology. I think it’ll really be cool to have that new exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are you working on any new upcoming projects?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W: I’m currently working on a big—well, a medium sized mecha comic, so giant fighting robots. I won’t have that at the fair, but I will be doing reprints of my series Precinct X99 volumes one and two which have be out of print for a while.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Neta Bomani</name></author><summary type="html">An illustration of Wren McDonald drawing by Wren McDonald. Image description: A cartoon of a boyishly looking person hunched over a drafter’s desk with a backpack on. The person is drawing a smiley face sticking its tongue out. There is also a mechanical cord attached to the back of the person’s head. I interviewed illustrator and cartoonist Wren McDonald. Not only has Wren’s work been featured in publications such as the New York Times, Wired and Boom! Studios, but Wren is also preceded by a long line of artists engaged in the cyberpunk genre, from Paul Verhoeven to Katsuhiro Otomo. Wren will be a vendor at the first ever New York Tech Zine Fair on Dec. 1 from 12-7 p.m. at the School for Poetic Computation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Amy Wibowo on femininity, making cute zines and decolonizing technology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/in-conversation-with-amy-wibowo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amy Wibowo on femininity, making cute zines and decolonizing technology" /><published>2018-11-25T16:35:06-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-25T16:35:06-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/in-conversation-with-amy-wibowo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/in-conversation-with-amy-wibowo.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/amy_wibowo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Amy Wibowo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;BubbleSort Zines founder, Amy Wibowo. Image description: A portrait featuring Amy. She/they are pictured in the center and looking off to the right on a navy blue background. Image courtesy Techies Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the &lt;a href=&quot;/&quot;&gt;New York Tech Zine Fair&lt;/a&gt;, I interviewed founder, editor and CEO of &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.bubblesort.io/&quot;&gt;BubbleSort Zines&lt;/a&gt;, Amy Wibowo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amy is a programmer who left the tech industry to pursue her life’s work of making zines for women, femmes and non-binary folks who feel alienated by gender discrimination within and out of the computer science field. Amy will be a featured vendor at the first ever New York Tech Zine Fair on Dec. 1 from 12 to 7 p.m. at the School for Poetic Computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your zines involve a lot of research, care and content and often extend to upwards of 100 pages. What is your zine-making process?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amy: There’s a lot of research. I did study computer science formally, so sometimes I go back and look at my notes and my textbooks. I try to think about what concepts were most exciting to me, what concepts were the most difficult to me, and get myself back into the mindset of when I first learned about these things. A lot of writing, a lot of drawing. I tend to alternate between the two — like, when I’m tired of writing, I work on the illustrations and when I’m tired of illustrating, I go back to writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s really important to me that people can understand the zines even if they don’t have a computer science background or heavy math background. I have a test reader who’s a high school student go through all the zines and tell me if certain parts are boring, if certain parts are hard to understand. They will let me know I need to rewrite those sections. The drawings make a big difference. Her feedback is often, “more drawings, please!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also important for me to make sure the content I’m writing is not only easy to understand, but technically accurate. I’m not an expert in every subject in computer science by any means, so I make sure to get someone who is an expert in a subject that I’m writing to read through the zine and make sure the analogies I use make sense or the way I introduce the subject won’t cause misunderstandings or be a problem if the reader wants to go into the subject more deeply later. Then, a lot of revising and editing. Maybe 90 percent of my time is actually re-writing the zine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How long is the process from start to finish?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: About 6 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/zines.png&quot; alt=&quot;BubbleSort Zines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An assortment of BubbleSort Zines. Image description: A top down view of zines spread out like a fan surrounded by femme lego toys, plushies, hearts and pink, pastel pink and fuchsia art markers. One of the zine’s titles can be read as “How do calculators even.”
Are there any specific printing, zine-making techniques you consider integral to the BubbleSort look?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: I don’t print them myself. I get them printed locally. As a small, woman run, independent business, I try to find — in any part of my process — other small, independent woman run businesses as well. I have a connection with a woman run, local printer in Oakland. It’s important to me in my process to support other small, marginalized independent business. When I hire test readers, I prioritize finding ones that are femme or queer or people of color and/or intersections of all those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you find it challenging to find people within those intersections?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: So far it hasn’t been a problem. I usually tweet asking if there’s any interest for whatever particular thing I need — models, photographers, readers and the internet is usually quick to provide. For me, it has the bonus of my business getting to pay other marginalized people which makes me happy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/how_does_the_internet.png&quot; alt=&quot;BubbleSort Zines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Screenshot of a spread from Amy Wibowo’s “How does the internet” zine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I understand crowdsourcing is an important factor in your process. How would you describe your relationship with people on social media or, more generally, the audience who interacts with your zines?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: I feel really lucky to have the audience that I do. My audience is anyone who cares about computer science. I think my youngest readers are 8 years old. I have 70 year old women stop by my booth at a zine fest and tell me they’re really curious about how the internet works and then buy a zine about how the internet works. I feel like my audience is really supportive of my work. It makes me feel really happy and touched when I get emails from people saying that my zines helped them get through a computer science class or helped their daughter discover an interest in computer science. I hope through my zines I can be kind of like a personal cheerleader for anyone when they’re feeling discouraged about tech and computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;When you were first getting into computer science, were there times where you felt like giving up?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: I felt pretty lucky when I was doing computer science in college in that, I went to an engineering school, but lived in an all women’s dorm. In all of my classes, I always had groups of women that I would work with. It was more of a shock when I graduated and started working to see that wouldn’t always be the case. I do remember in some of my college classes, I was criticized for being femme and having a feminine approach to computer science. I remember peer reviews telling me that —&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;From your fellow femme/women peers?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: No, male peers telling me that my final project presentation was too pink. That definitely informs my process now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time I’m criticized for my work being too feminine, I just want to make it more feminine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;With your zines being more feminine, does your audience reflect that? Are people who you didn’t expect to your zines to resonate with interacting and engaging with your work?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: One thing that makes me happy is that I definitely receive emails from men thanking me for not calling them “zines for women” because there are a lot of men and non-binary people who also like cute and feminine things and are often excluded from a traditional focus in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What do you think sets apart your zines from other tech zines?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: The things I try to focus on in particular are history and art that aren’t often connected to computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to decolonize computer science education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of CS classes will focus on contributions from white, western men. There are lot of interesting contributions from other cultures and women and people of color and intersections of all of those. I try to make sure to emphasize those. I also try to focus on the bigger picture and things that might be helpful to learn even if someone doesn’t end up going into computer science. I feel like technology is increasingly more and more a part of everyday life, so it’s useful for people to learn about security or how the internet works even if they don’t end up studying computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;In your research of a non western computer science history, who are some of the figures you were surprised or inspired by?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: This is not a specific person, but I thought it was really cool that a lot of cryptographic advancements were made by Muslim scholars of the Quran. It happened many centuries before western cryptographers made the same discoveries. A lot of times it’s cultural discoveries and not just individual discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;You talk a lot about reframing computer science as magical in efforts to make it accessible and inclusive to people who might not think there is a place for them in computer science. Why is it important to reframe and/or decolonize computer science as non western and/or more magical to challenge the prescriptive way we understand computer science?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: One thing that happens as a result of the typical framing of computer science as very logical and scientific is people can often feel like it’s infallible or impossible for it to be biased or that it’s completely neutral and non political, when it’s not any of those things because computer science is something done by humans and humans can be biased and racist and yeah, infuse everything they do with politics. It’s important to remember that computer science is something very human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I feel like zine culture is telling me ‘anyway that you are, anyway that your zines are, that’s valid.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the current preconception of computer science also includes who can be in tech and who can be a programmer and that’s something I want to see eliminated. Whereas the perception of computer science as magic I feel is something that’s more for everyone. I also think there are preconceptions of what sorts of things you can do with technology, like building apps and websites similar to the ones that already exist. I like the idea of framing computer science around fiction, fantasy or science fiction to help people not be locked into the ideas or apps and websites they’ve already seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The narratives around technology today can be very dystopian. How do you hold onto and share the magic you find in computer science and tech despite all the negativity surrounding it?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: It can be really hard, but that’s actually my primary motivation for everything I do. In fact, I’ve been trying to rediscover the magic I used to feel about computer science right when I started learning it and then pass that onto other people. It’s almost always through a personal creative project connecting computer science to knitting or origami or cross stitching or embroidery or other crafts that makes me rekindle the magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can you recall a moment you felt magic with a computer?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember learning about logic circuits for the first time and feeling like that was really magical because I always used calculators but never understood how they worked. I knew it was possible for machines to do physical labor for us, but it felt really magical to learn about how they could also do thinking and computational work for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/hello_world.png&quot; alt=&quot;BubbleSort Zines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Hello world” illustration by Amy Wibowo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How have you felt entering the zine community as feminine person compared to the tech industry?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: Oh, it felt so much more welcoming. As a person who is typically in tech spaces, entering zine spaces feels like a great recharge for my soul. First of all, seeing the types of people in the zine community — there are so many more people of color and queer people. The kinds of things people write zines about — zines about sexuality or being an immigrant or being mixed raced and knowing that there’s an audience for each of these things. Things are so personal. Everyone who writes zines about each of these topics — they’re like pouring their heart and soul into it. When I read zines I feel really connected to the people who wrote them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’m curious about your transition and whether or not you experienced any growing pains in the shift from the tech industry into the zine community. Did you experience imposter syndrome or feel like you were making a mistake?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: One thing I love about the zine community and zine culture is I feel like it’s really hard to feel imposter syndrome in it because there are such a wide ranges of zines — zines that are hand written, zines that are photo copied — it feels so validating. I feel like zine culture is telling me “anyway that you are, anyway that your zines are, that’s valid.” In the past, I’ve thought about writing a computer science textbook or book, but with writing books I often think to myself, “oh i don’t know that I know enough yet to write a book, I don’t consider myself an expert.”I feel like there isn’t that kind of gatekeeping in the zine community. However much I know about a subject, it’s okay for me to write a zine about it. I can not know about a subject and learn about it and write about it. So that’s been really nice and fulfilling compared to the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing is that, most people making zines, don’t make zines as there primary source of income. So trying to figure out the business piece, the sustainability piece has been difficult and I’ve had to learn a lot to figure how to make a sustainable amount of money running a zine business compared to the tech industry where I felt very spoiled. Tech salaries are much easier to live on. It’s definitely a process. I feel more hopeful about it, there are still definitely some struggles, especially living in San Francisco which is not a cheap place to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also been branching out into apparel. There are ways that the apparel side of my business is helping keep the zines and educational side of my business more sustainable. A couple weeks of designing a shirt will bring in just as much money as six months of researching and writing a zine. I’m trying to figure out ways that still resonate with my core mission of making computer science more inclusive, but still make my business more sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/bomber_jackets.png&quot; alt=&quot;BubbleSort Zines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;BubbleSort bomber jackets. Image description: Four models pictured sitting at a counter while showing off the back of their jackets which read “git it gurl” in cursive hand lettering surrounded by illustrations of cherries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do you keep your zines in conversation with your merch?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: I’ve thought a lot about how there’s kind of a tech bro uniform of hoodies and jeans and I feel like that’s one of the methods of gatekeeping feminine people out of computer science and programming. It’s very clear feminine people don’t have that uniform. A lot of my merch has pastel colors and also includes technical jokes or technical references. Instead of a programming hoodie, I’m making programming satin bomber jackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;This might be a redundant question given our conversation, but I do want to verify whether or not you consider yourself to be critical toward the tech industry. If so, what are the challenges?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: Yeah, I still consider myself to be very critical toward the tech industry which is kind of interesting, contradictory, ironic because I am writing resources to teach computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While wanting to make computer science more inclusive for the people who are entering it, I continue to be more critical of the tech industry so it deserves all of the marginalized people that are entering it.
So many things bother me the way the tech industry thinks of itself as above and beyond ethics or law, thinking of itself as more important than art or the humanities, the way it continues to gatekeep marginalized people, the way that so many algorithms are biased against dark skinned people — so much of that needs fixing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of your criticality involves a lot of emotional and intellectual labor to help people, particularly cis men and their collaborators, understand femininity isn’t a sign of unintelligence and the tech industry should be more inclusive. How do you navigate knowing when to explain yourself vs conserve your energy to people who discriminate against you and the people you’re making space for in this industry?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: It’s really hard. I’ve shifted more and more toward letting my work speak for itself. If I’m feeling like I have some extra energy, I’ll sometimes try to explain to people who question what I do — if they’re a friend, a colleague, or a friend of a friend — people who I’m more adjacent to socially might be more willing to listen. It’s still exhausting just to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yeah, I feel you. I don’t want to take up too much more of your time and energy. Any last words? Are you working on any upcoming projects?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: I’m currently working on writing a zine about operating systems. Some other zines I have in the pipeline are: a zine about machine learning, a zine about compilers, a zine with interviews with some of my favorite coders — people who are using coding for social issues, art or music, and a zine about witchy trigonometry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/workshop.png&quot; alt=&quot;BubbleSort Zines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Amy doing a workshop at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WriteSpeakCode/status/1024749999467442177&quot;&gt;Write/Speak/Code&lt;/a&gt; in 2018. Image description: Amy is pictured in the center behind a laptop, mid sentence, holding one of her/their zines and a microphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ooh, “witchy trigonometry?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: [Laughs]. It’s a zine that explains how to calculate the phases of the moon using trigonometry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wow. That’s amazing. What are you looking forward to for the New York Tech Zine Fair?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: I’m really excited about the New York Tech Zine Fair because I’ve never been to a zine fair that was specifically focused on tech zines. I love SFPC and all of the work I’ve seen come out of it. I feel like it’s such a perfect host for a tech zine fair because they have everything I love about tech and zines — like the creativity, the inclusivity. I’m really excited to walk around and see what other people have made and buy lots of zines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog/computing_stories.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BubbleSort Zines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Computing &amp;amp; Stories Summit co-organized by Linda Liukas and Taeyoon Choi, featuring presenters Amy Wibowo, Jie Qi, Jenna Register, and Natalie Freed, assistant organizer Natalia Cabrera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Would you consider zine making itself a technology?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: At SFPC last year, I participated in Computing and Stories conference. Most people talked about how they used books and stories as a way to talk about technical concepts. Natalie Freed talked about how the art of bookbinding was a very technical thing and how there were different techniques around bookbinding — she had written a theorem of bookbinding and proved it to us with topology. I hadn’t ever thought of it in the converse, but yes, bookmaking is super technical. While that isn’t they way I’ve approached it, I love hearing from other people who have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;You’ll be doing a workshop, right? What is it going to be about?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: Yeah, I will be. It’s going to be a zine writing workshop. It’s about zines as a way to make complex topics more accessible and understandable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amy’s workshop titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/amy-wibowo-zines-as-a-friendly-introduction-to-complex-concepts-tickets-52724458274&quot;&gt;“Zines as a Friendly Introduction to Complex Topics”&lt;/a&gt; will be on Dec. 1 from 1 to 2 p.m. at the New York Tech Zine Fair.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Neta Bomani</name></author><summary type="html">BubbleSort Zines founder, Amy Wibowo. Image description: A portrait featuring Amy. She/they are pictured in the center and looking off to the right on a navy blue background. Image courtesy Techies Project.</summary></entry></feed>